Guide to the Nichols Family Correspondence
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Nichols family correspondence
1769-1873
OSB MSS 154
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
6.67
(19 boxes)
The Nichols Family Correspondence consists almost entirely of letters addressed to the three generations of the Nichols family who owned the printing firm Nichols & Co. and edited and published the Gentleman's Magazine from 1778 to 1856. The letters document a portion of the publication history of the magazine, particularly the professional and personal relationships between the Nicholses and their contributors. The collection also documents other publication projects of Nichols & Co., as well as the Nichols's antiquarian and literary interests.
Nichols family
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Winifred Myers on the James Marshall and Marie-Louise Osborn Fund, 1972-1975.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Nichols Family
John Nichols (1745-1826), English master printer, editor, author, and antiquarian, inherited his printing business from his partner William Bowyer. Nichols printed for learned societies and published many county histories, including his own History and Antiquities of the Town and County of Leicester (1795-1812). Nichols purchased a share in the popular Gentleman's Magazine in 1778; he and his descendants edited and printed the monthly until 1856. He also produced collections of literary anecdotes of eighteenth century authors, a biography of Hogarth, and literary editions. In 1810 he became a Fellow of the Society of Antiquaries in London.
John Bowyer Nichols (1779-1863), the son of John Nichols by his second wife, succeeded his father as owner of Nichols & Co. and as editor of the Gentleman's Magazine. He too was a noted antiquarian, publishing a number of county histories and printing many antiquarian articles in his magazine. His extensive involvement in the Parliamentary printing business resulted in his testifying twice before Parliamentary commissions investigating the high cost of official printing. Nichols was a Fellow of the Society of Antiquaries and an original member of the Novomagians, their select dining club. His many antiquarian works included Historical Notices of Fonthill Abbey, Wiltshire (1836).
John Gough Nichols (1806-1873), the eldest son of John Bowyer Nichols, began attending meetings of the Society of Antiquaries with his father when he was twelve years old. Nichols grew up to become a prominent antiquarian, helping to found the Camden Society (1838), the Archaeological Institute (1844), and the London and Middlesex Archaeological Society (1855). Among his publications are Autographs of Royal, Noble, Learned and Remarkable Personages (1829) and Examples of Decorative Tiles, Sometimes termed Encaustic (1841–5). While he was best known as an antiquary and scholar, he continued to run the family printing business until his death in 1873, and he edited the Gentleman's Magazine until its sale in 1856.
Scope and Contents
The Nichols Family Correspondence consists almost entirely of letters received by John Nichols, John Bowyer Nichols, and John Gough Nichols.The collection primarily documents the editing and publication of the Gentleman's Magazine by three generations of the Nichols family, as well as other aspects of their publishing business, Nichols & Co. There is also much correspondence concerning the Nichols's antiquarian interests and promotion of learned societies, as well as some family correspondence from various relatives and among the printers themselves.
Arrangement
Organized into one series: I. Correspondence, 1769-1873.
Gentleman's magazine (London, England); Antiquarians -- Great Britain; Authors, English -- 19th century; Authors and publishers -- Great Britain; Publishers and publishing -- Great Britain; Periodicals -- Publishing -- Great Britain; Printers -- Great Britain; Akerman, John Yonge, 1806-1873; Blore, Thomas, 1764-1818; Bray, William, 1736-1832; Brydges, Egerton, Sir, 1762-1837; Burney, Charles P. (Charles Parr), 1785-1864; Ellis, Henry, 1777-1869; Fisher, Thomas, 1781?-1836; Hackett, Maria, 1783-1874; Hoare, Richard Colt, Sir, 1758-1838; Hutchinson, William, 1732-1814; Nichols, J. B. (John Bowyer), 1779-1863; Nichols, John Gough, 1806-1873; Nichols, John, 1745-1826; Nichols family; Palmer, Joseph, 1756-1815; Rosser, W. H. (William Henry); Taylor, John, 1757-1832; Young, Charles George, Sir, 1795-1869; Nichols & Co. (London, England)
- Correspondence, 1769-1873; Series I; 6.67; (19 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Correspondence consists primarily of business letters received by John Nichols, John Bowyer Nichols, and John Gough Nichols. Many of the letters are from authors whose work appeared in the popular and influential Gentleman's Magazine. Subjects include articles submitted for the magazine; letters to the editor and corrections of previous articles; business arrangements; and subscription and advertising negotiations.
  Many correspondents also discuss antiquarian and historical topics, including archaeological finds and numismatics, often in the context of proposing articles for Gentleman's Magazine or longer works for publication by Nichols & Co. Major correspondents include John Yonge Akerman, Thomas Blore, William Bray, Sir Egerton Brydges, Sir Henry Ellis, Maria Cantwell, Sir Richard Colt Hoare, Joseph Palmer, and Sir Charles George Young. There is also a small amount of personal and family correspondence among the printers themselves and with other members of the Nichols family.
  Detailed folder notes in the box and folder list highlight the main topics of many correspondents' letters. A few correspondent files contain corrected proof, research notes, or drafts of articles. Box 19 contains unidentified correspondence; two folders of printer's proof for articles; and research and other notes.
  - Adams, Thomas. ALS to Nichols & Co., Shaftesbury, 1828 Feb 20 (Box 1)
    Requests certain illustrations and discusses the possibility of reprinting a book. With draft reply by John Bowyer Nichols.
  - Agutter, William, 1758-1835. 2 ALS to John Nichols, Magdalen College, 1786 Oct 7-1787 Jan 15 (Box 1)
    About articles in the Gentleman's Magazine.
  - Akerman, John Yonge, 1806-1873
    - 21 ALS to John Gough Nichols, [v.p.], 1832 Oct 20-1839 Feb 13 (Box 1)
      On numismatic and antiquarian subjects. Includes Akerman's article, "The Portraits on the Coins of the Twelve Caesars," which was published in the Gentleman's Magazine.
    - ALS to John Gough Nichols, [n.p.], 1835 Apr (Box 1)
      Returning proofs.
    - ALS to John Gough Nichols, Pancras Lane, [n.y.] Nov 15 (Box 1)
  - Allan, George, 1767-1828. AL (3d person) to John Nichols, James Park, 1818 Apr 24 (Box 1)
    Book order.
  - Allen, Joseph. ALS to [John Bowyer Nichols], Kensington Cross, 1826 Sep 7 (Box 1)
    About a financial agreement.
  - Amyot, Thomas, 1775-1850. ALS to [John Bowyer Nichols], James St., 1825 Mar 24 (Box 1)
  - Atkinson, George. ALS to [John Bowyer Nichols], Hull, 1848 May 19 (Box 1)
    Asks to have his name added to the list of subscribers for Nichols's forthcoming work.
  - Babington, Matthew D. ALS to Nichols & Co., Rothley Temple, 1815 Mar 7 (Box 2)
    Asks that the Appendix to the History of Leicestershire be sent to his new address.
  - Bailey, N. N. ALS to Nichols & Co., Tower, 1832 Mar 24 (Box 2)
  - Baker, W. L. ALS to John Bowyer Nichols, Hargrave, 1847 Mar 17 (Box 2)
    Congratulates Nichols on his son's marriage.
  - Baldwin, Charles. ALS to John Bowyer Nichols, New Bishop St., 1846 Nov 17 (Box 2)
    Asks Nichols to mention the marriage of his niece in the next Gentleman's Magazine.
  - Baldwin, George, 1743?-1826. ALS to John Bowyer Nichols, Knox Rut[?], 1818 Dec 22 (Box 2)
    Promises to meet on 29 December although his wife and daughter may be absent.
  - Bandinel, Bulkeley, 1781-1861. ALS to Nichols & Co., Bodleian Library, 1830 Oct 22 (Box 2)
    Answer to query in the Gentleman's Magazine.
  - Barrington, Jane Elizabeth (Liddell) Barrington, Viscountess, 1804-1883. AL (3d person) to Miss Nichols, Cavendish Square, 1853 Nov 18 (Box 2)
    Sends her regrets.
  - Barrington, Shute, Bp. of Durham, 1734-1826. AL (3d person) to John Nichols, Cavendish Square, 1817 Mar 14 (Box 2)
    Sends prints.
  - Barrow, Mr. AL (3d person) to Nichols & Co., Admiralty, 1853 Nov 7 (Box 2)
    About engravings.
  - Bayley, John Whitcomb, d. 1869. ALS to Nichols & Co., Tower of London, 1831 Sep 27 (Box 2)
    Requests the immediate return of some copies of his History and Antiquities of Tower of London.
  - Beale, Mr. AL (3d person) to Mrs. Nichols, Rose Cottage, 1836 Mar 14 (Box 2)
  - Beattie, Mr. AL (3d person) to John Nichols, Shrewsbury, 1826 Mar 8 (Box 2)
    Asks him to convey letter to Joseph Cradock.
  - Behnes, William, d. 1864. 2 ALS to Nichols & Co., Regents Park, 1857 Feb 26 (Box 2)
    Arranges to examine his work.
  - Beliogard, W. ALS to John Bowyer Nichols, Highgate, 1855 Jul 18 (Box 2)
  - Bellamy, B. P. ALS to [John Bowyer Nichols?], Bath, 1842 Nov 18 (Box 2)
    Acknowledges receipt of autographs.
  - Bellins, Samuel. AL (3d person) to Thomas Fisher, Camden Town, [n.y.] Nov 6 (Box 2)
    About engraving plates in Mr. Fisher's possession.
  - Beloe, William, 1758-1817. ALS to John Bowyer Nichols, [n.p.], 1813 Feb 11 (Box 2)
    About a subscription to the Gentleman's Magazine.
  - Belt, Robert. ALS to John Bowyer Nichols, [n.p.], [n.y.] Mar 18 (Box 2)
    Regrets his inability to see Nichols and his wife that evening.
  - Beltz, George Frederick, 1777-1841
    - 4 ALS to John Bowyer Nichols, Heralds College, 1823 Jan 18-1828 Jan 4 (Box 2)
      About engravings, designs, and the Society of Antiquaries.
    - ALS to John Bowyer Nichols, Heralds College, 1834 May 24 (Box 2)
      About the publication of the Scrope roll.
  - Bennett, James, d. ca. 1826. ALS to John Bowyer Nichols, Kentish Town, 1826 Aug 28 (Box 2)
  - Bentham, William. 2 ALS to John Bowyer Nichols, [n.p.], 1819 (Box 2)
    Book and magazine orders.
  - Bentinck, Lord William Henry Cavendish, 1774-1839. AL (3d person) to Nichols & Co., [n.p], 1809 Mar 6 (Box 2)
    Concerns repairs for a book and subscription orders.
  - Bentley, Edward. ALS to John Bowyer Nichols, Ely Place, 1826 Mar 17 (Box 2)
    About electioneering.
  - Bentley, H. ALS to [John Bowyer Nichols?], Bank, 1826 Nov 17 (Box 2)
  - Betham, Sir William, 1779-1853
    - 3 ALS to John Bowyer Nichols, Dublin, 1826 Oct 9-1832 May 21 (Box 2)
      Concerns Betham's articles for the Gentleman's Magazine. Includes letter to editor of the magazine.
    - 7 ALS to John Gough Nichols, Dublin, 1831 Jan 19-1844 Jan 31 (Box 2)
      About antiquarian matters and the Gentleman's Magazine. Betham objects to criticism of his works by magazine reviewers.
  - Bethell, Christopher, Bp. of Bangor, 1773-1859. AL (3d person) to Nichols & Co., Westminster, n.d. (Box 2)
    Requests Nichols to print 500 copies of a pamphlet entitled, "Advise after Confirmation." A copy accompanies the letter.
  - Bigland, R. ALS to John Nichols, [n.p.], 1805 Apr 17 (Box 2)
  - Bingham, Peregrine, 1754-1826. 5 ALS to John Nichols, Eastham, 1803 Oct 17-1807 Nov 2 (Box 2)
    Correspondence with his publisher about historical research, the Gentleman's Magazine, subscriptions and book orders.
  - Bingham, S. 3 ALS to Nichols & Co., Brook St., Bath, [1801 or later]-1803 Dec 23 (Box 2)
    About subscription to his father's works and the proofs of the Gentleman's Magazine.
  - Bingham, William, 1771-1810. ALS to John Nichols, Calmely, Bristol, Somerset, 1803 Oct 25 (Box 2)
    Inquires about book written by his sister.
  - Bingley, William, 1774-1823. ALS to John Nichols, Christchurch, 1805 Dec 21 (Box 2)
    Sends a critique for publication in the Gentleman's Magazine.
  - Bischoff, James. ALS to John Bowyer Nichols, Barryhall St., 1826 Nov 10 (Box 2)
    About the Gentleman's Magazine.
  - Bishop, Mary (Palmer). AL (3d person) to John Nichols, Hampstead, 1797 Jul 4 (Box 2)
    Thanks Nichols for his review of her late husband's poetry.
  - Bisset, Mr. AL to John Nichols, [n.p.], [ca. 1812] (Box 2)
    About publications for Gentleman's Magazine.
  - Blackwood, C. 2 ALS to John Nichols, Brunswick Square, 1815 Apr 30-May 14 (Box 2)
    Asks Nichols as a member of the Literary Fund Society to help a writer's widow.
  - Blackwood, Sir Henry, 1770-1832. ALS to John Bowyer Nichols, Devizes, 1823 Oct 9 (Box 2)
    About ship departures.
  - Blackwood, William, 1776-1834. ALS to Nichols & Co., Edinburgh, 1809 Feb 23 (Box 2)
    On the book trade. Includes draft reply.
  - Blagney, Mr. AL (3d person) to Nichols & Co., Hanover Sq., 1814 May 6 (Box 2)
    Orders the eighth volume of Literary Anecdotes.
  - Bland, Michel. ALS to John Bowyer Nichols, Montague Place, 1818 Oct 2 (Box 2)
    Thanks for her father's obituary in the Gentleman's Magazine.
  - Bland, Miss. AL (3d person) to John Nichols, Grove Hill, 1804 May 14 (Box 2)
    Printing order.
  - Bliss, Philip, d. 1803. 2 ALS to John Nichols, Frampton Cotterell near Bristol, 1798 Oct 26 (Box 2)
    Agrees to subscribe to the History of Leicester and introduces his eldest son.
  - Bliss, Philip, 1787-1857. 21 ALS to John Nichols, Oxford, 1806 Dec 2-1821 Dec 12 (Box 2)
    On business and personal matters. Bliss did research at the Bodleian Library for works published by Nichols.
  - Blomfield, Charles James, Bp. of London, 1786-1857
    - Letter (copy) to Richard Harvey, Fulham, 1846 Jul 28 (Box 2)
      He [John Nichols] was amongst the earliest and most diligent of those, who cultivated that taste for English Antiquities, and for biographical anecdote. In a word, he was no unworthy successor of his old friend & partner, Bowyer.
    - ALS to John Bowyer Nichols, Dunton, [n.y.] Jul 8 (Box 2)
      Reveals his authorship of an article for the Gentleman's Magazine.
  - Bloomfield, S. T. ALS to John Nichols, Parsonage Tugby, 1818 Nov 12 (Box 2)
  - Blore, Edward, 1787-1879. ALS to John Bowyer Nichols, London (Box 2)
    Regrets that he has no letters of Sir Walter Scott's that can be printed; also a letter from his wife, undated, that Blore is ill.
  - Blore, Thomas, 1764-1818. 22 ALS to John Nichols, [v.p.], 1791 Dec 13-1811 Dec 26 (Box 2)
    On business and personal matters, including Blore's histories, genealogies, answers to letters to the Gentleman's Magazine and antiquarian subjects.
  - Boaden, James, 1762-1839. 2 ALS to John Bowyer Nichols, Warren St., Fitzroy Square, 1831 Sep 16,Dec 1 (Box 2)
    Thanks Nichols for a kind review of one of his works and asks to borrow copies of the Gentleman's Magazine for the last ten years.
  - Bomor, T. ALS to Nichols & Co., Fentonville, 1807 Jan 26 (Box 2)
    Thanks the publishers for "having so kindly offered to notice my prospective itineracy in your magazine, which is so justly esteemed by the discerning antiquary and scientific observer."
  - Bonney, Henry Kaye, 1780-1862. ALS to John Nichols, Cliffe, near Wansford, 1813 Oct 4 (Box 2)
    Proposes the publication of a history of Fotheringay. Accompanied by draft reply from Nichols.
  - Booker, Luke, 1762-1835. 9 ALS to John Bowyer Nichols, Dudley Vicarage, 1810 Aug 10-1831 Jul 20 (Box 2)
    Friendly letters concerning food, family and the Gentleman's Magazine.
  - Boscawen, William, 1752-1811. 2 ALS to John Nichols, Victualling Office, 1797 Oct 10-1798 Jan 10 (Box 3)
    On the Royal Literary Fund.
  - Bosvile, Thomas. ALS to Nichols & Co., Lincolnshire, 1815 Jun 5 (Box 3)
    Payment for books.
  - Boswell, Edward, 1760-1842. ALS to Nichols & Co., [n.p.], 1832 Nov 18 (Box 3)
    Asks Nichols to print subscription lists and table of contents for The Civil Division of the County of Dorset in the Gentleman's Magazine.
  - Boucher, Jonathan, 1738-1804. 3 ALS to John Nichols, Epsom, 1780 Oct 31-1792 Oct 14 (Box 3)
    Offers manuscripts and begs for space in the Gentleman's Magazine.
  - Bowdler, Thomas, 1754-1825. ALS to Nichols & Co., Isle of Wight, 1809 Nov 29 (Box 3)
    Asks for corrections in one of his works published by Nichols.
  - Bowen, H. M. ALS to John Bowyer Nichols, [n.p.], 1826 Dec (Box 3)
    On printing and personal business.
  - Bowles, William Lisle, 1762-1850. 4 ALS, 1 AL (3d person) to John Bowyer Nichols, [v.p.], 1821 May 2-1833 Sep 3 (Box 3)
    On business and literary affairs. Two ALSs describe his argument with Byron over Pope. Discloses his admiration for Byron's "brillance" and calls their differences more of a "colloquy" than a "controversy."
  - Bowstead, James, Bp. of Lichfield, d. 1843. ALS to Nichols & Co., Berkeley Sq., 1840 Feb 28 (Box 3)
  - Boyd, Hugh Stuart, 1781-1848. ALS to John Bowyer Nichols, Hawley Square, Margate, n.d. (Box 3)
    Sends translation of Sophocles for publication in the Gentleman's Magazine.
  - Boys, John. ALS to [Nichols & Co.], Hawley Sq., Margate, 1809 Oct 29 (Box 3)
    Asks for help in reprinting the History of Thanet.
  - Boys, William, 1735-1803. ALS to John Nichols, Sandwich, 1787 Sep 2 (Box 3)
  - Bradfield, Thomas. LS to John Bowyer Nichols, Derby St., 1825 Dec 13 (Box 3)
  - Bradley, J. 3 ALS to John Nichols, Lincoln, 1772 Oct 25 (Box 3)
    Concerns books and antiquarian subjects.
  - Bradney, Joseph. ALS to [Nichols & Co.], Surrey, 1810 Jul 4 (Box 3)
    Order for books.
  - Brady, John Henry. 4 ALS to Nichols & Co., [v.p.], 1821 Jul 16-1827 May 5 (Box 3)
    Business and personal letters about republication of his father's poetry, health and reviews for the Gentleman's Magazine.
  - Bray, S. P. ALS to John Bowyer Nichols, The Vicarage, Tavistock, 1846 Nov 5 (Box 3)
    Personal letter about his illness which he feels was caused by the death of his brother.
  - Bray, William, 1736-1832
    - 2 ALS and 1 AL (3d person) to [John Nichols], Great Russell Street, 1801 Sep 23-[ca. 1809] (Box 3)
      Expresses his determination to see his friend Owen Manning's History of Surrey completed.
    - 40 ALS, 1 LS to John Bowyer Nichols, Shere, 1822 Jul 5-1832 Jun 12 (Box 3)
      Letters between antiquarian and printer concerning Bray's publications, including The History of Surrey, corrections of proof, engravings, and the Gentleman's Magazine.
  - Braybrooke, Richard Griffin, 2d Baron, 1750-1825. 2 ALS and 2 AL (3d person) to John Nichols, Audley, 1798 Jan 2-1816 Feb 8 (Box 3)
    Orders for books.
  - Braybrooke, Richard Griffin, 3d Baron, 1783-1858. ALS to John Bowyer Nichols, Audley, 1827 Jan 24 (Box 3)
  - Brayley, Edward William, 1802-1870. ALS to John Bowyer Nichols, London Institute, 1836 Apr 12 (Box 3)
    Accounts for book he borrowed in 1831. On verso is Nichols' draft reply.
  - Brayley, Edward Wedlake, 1773-1854. AL (3d person) to Nichols & Co., [n.p.], n.d. (Box 3)
    Allows his letter to be inserted in the Gentleman's Magazine.
  - Breck, John, b. 1740. ALS to [John Nichols], Ellismore in Shropshire, 1786 Mar 2 (Box 3)
    Inquires to whom he should apply "to come at a Vicarage in the Dioc. of Lich."
  - Breton, Thomas. ALS to [John Nichols], [n.p.], 1802 (Box 3)
    Description of week's activity.
  - Brewer, George, b. 1766. ALS to [John Bowyer Nichols?], Blackfriars Road, 1806 Jul 8 (Box 3)
    Asks for relief from the Royal Literary Fund.
  - Brewer, James Norris, fl. 1799-1829. 5 ALS to John Nichols, [v.p.], 1815 Jul 10-1820 Mar 22 (Box 3)
    Asks for assistance in literary and personal pursuits. Thanks Nichols for nominating him for membership in the Society of Antiquaries but wants to know why his application was rejected.
  - Brewer, Richard. ALS to [John Nichols?], Margate, 1794 Aug 25 (Box 3)
    Business transaction.
  - Brewin, John. ALS to John Nichols, Aileston, 1804 Sep 14 (Box 3)
    Response to antiquarian inquiries.
  - Brewster, John, 1753-1842. ALS to John Nichols, Stockton-upon-Tees, n.d. (Box 3)
  - Bridge, Thomas. ALS to John Bowyer Nichols, The Lodge, n.d. (Box 3)
    Invitation to dinner.
  - Bridges, Julia J. ALS to John Bowyer Nichols, [n.p.], 1838 Dec (Box 3)
  - Bridges, Nathaniel. ALS to John Nichols, Willoughby, 1814 Aug 25 (Box 3)
    Response to questions about the history of his county.
  - Britton, John, 1771-1857
    - 14 ALS, 3 AL (3d person) to John Nichols, Tavistock Place, 1805 Nov 12-1812 Dec 5 (Box 3)
      On antiquarian and topographical subjects.
    - 10 ALS to John Bowyer Nichols, London, 1816 Dec 27-1829 Oct 20 (Box 3)
      Includes book orders and requests, antiquarian queries, and materials for the Gentleman's Magazine.
  - Brockedon, William, 1787-1854. ALS to John Bowyer Nichols, 1854 Jan 30 (Box 3)
    Asks Nichols to back his son-in- law's candidacy for the Athenaeum.
  - Bromet, W.
    - ALS to John Bowyer Nichols, Freemason Tavern, 1844 May 2 (Box 3)
      Asks name of boarding house.
    - ALS to John Gough Nichols, [n.p.], 1839 Apr 18 (Box 3)
      Correction for publication.
  - Bromhead, Catherine. ALS to [John Nichols], Lincoln, 1786 Aug 17 (Box 3)
  - Bromhead, Edward. 2 ALS to [John Nichols], Stapleford, Leicester, 1798 Jan 8 (Box 3)
    Information about the County of Leicester.
  - Bromwich, Bryan I'Anson. 4 ALS to John Nichols, [v.p.], 1785 Apr 10-1810 Mar 4 (Box 3)
    Sends manuscripts for publication. Includes letter to the editor of the Gentleman's Magazine about fire prevention and the virtues of a newly invented iron roof.
  - Brooke, Edward. 2 ALS to John Nichols, Wargrave, 1812 Sep 28-1813 Dec 22 (Box 3)
    Praises Nichol's "active engagement in the Cause of Literature." Also requests information about literary subjects.
  - Brooke, Frances (Moore), 1724-1789. 5 ALS to [John Nichols], [v.p.], n.d. (Box 3)
    On works for the Gentleman's Magazine, favors for her son, and book orders.
  - Brooke, John Moore, 1758-. ALS to John Nichols, Sleaford, Lincolnshire, 1789 Jan 26 (Box 3)
    Asks Nichols to publish certain of his mother's papers as a tribute.
  - Brooke, Joseph. ALS to John Nichols, Newark, 1801 Jan 29 (Box 3)
  - Brookes, Jane. ALS to John Nichols, [n.p.], 1808 Jan 6 (Box 3)
  - Brookes, Z. 2 ALS to John Gough Nichols, [n.p.], 1860 Aug 21-24 (Box 3)
    Concerns an article for the Gentleman's Magazine commemorating Edward and Edward David Evans, printsellers. Accompanied by draft reply.
  - Browell, Henry. ALS to John Nichols, Stable Yard, St. James, 1803 Oct 8 (Box 3)
    Asks for character reference.
  - Browne, John Henry, d. 1830. 6 ALS to John Nichols, Eakring, 1787 Feb 10-1817 Apr 17 (Box 3)
    Offers works for publication and requests favors for his nephew and adopted son John Henry Browne.
  - Browne, John Henry, 1767-1843. 3 ALS to Nichols & Co., Cotgrave, 1817 May 6-Jun 2 (Box 3)
    On publication of his pamphlet.
  - Browning, Frederick. ALS to [John Bowyer Nichols], Wallace St., 1815 Apr 6 (Box 3)
  - Brownlow, John Cust, 1st Earl, 1779-1853. ALS and AL (3d person) to Nichols & Co., Belton House, 1811 Jul 21-1826 Mar 12 (Box 3)
    On book orders and subscriptions.
  - Bruce, John, 1802-1869
    - 2 ALS to John Bowyer Nichols, [v.p.], 1834 Feb 8, 1835 Sep 21 (Box 3)
      About the possible publication of a series of Bruce's work in the Gentleman's Magazine and other literary projects in the Record Commission Office.
    - ALS to John Bowyer Nichols, Hastings, 1836 Jul 17 (Box 3)
      Asks Nichols to publish a review of his in the Gentleman's Magazine.
    - ALS to John Gough Nichols, Chelsea, 1839 Jan 7 (Box 3)
      About an index prepared by his sister-in-law and articles written by himself. The index accompanied the letter.
  - Bruer, M. ALS to John Gough Nichols, Dorset Square, 1855 Jun 23 (Box 3)
    Bruer is "very sorry that I cannot give you any information about Lord Stanhope."
  - Brydges, Sir Samuel Egerton, Bart., 1762-1832. 23 ALS to John Nichols, [v.p.], 1792 Jun 25-1818 Jan 8 (Box 3)